Okay, so let's do a comparison then of the
two methods.
So we did the zero method and the one
method.
Let's do a comparison of the two.
So here then, we have the two methods.
On the right-in side at the top is a zero
method.
At the bottom, on the left side,
is the one method.
So let's see what's the difference between
the two.
Well basically, what you'll notice is,
critical path, is exactly the same.
No change on the critical path.
A, D, E, H and I is the same in both.
Float values are exactly the same.
There's no change in the float value.
B has a float of three in the zero method.
B has a float of three in the one method.
C has a float of three in the zero method.
C has a flow of three in the one method.
Same with F and G.
Like both of them have a float of one in
the zero.
They both have a float of one in the one
method.
No change there.
Also, there's no change in the finish
dates.
Early finish, late finish.
For each activity is exactly the same.
If you look at B, it's 6 and 9.
For B, 6 and 9.
For C, 13 and 16.
For C, in the zero method, 13 and 16.
In the zero method, for F is 15 and 16.
For F, 15 and 16.
I, the end of the activity,
the rather I, end of
the project, still finishing
on day 19, 19 and 19.
The finished dates are exactly the same.
The only difference between the two
methods, the only difference in the two
diagrams that you can see is early start,
late start.
Left-hand side of the boxes.
In the one method, they have just been
increased by one
compared to the zero method.
So for A, you have a zero and a zero,
for A is one and one in the one method.
If you look at B, the early start is two,
late start is five.
for the zero method, for the one method,
is just increased by one, right?
Three and six.
For C, six and nine, in the zero,
in the one method, it's seven.
They've just been increased by one.
So in fact, if you have the zero method in
front of you, right, if you have the zero
method, the easiest way of
converting this into the one method
is simply by adding ones to
the left inside of the boxes.
That's it.
Just increase the early start
and late start by one for each
activity and you've simply
converted it into the one method.
That's it.
That's really essentially
the only difference
between the zero method
and the one method.
So all those calculations that we did
using the one method, right, remembering
when to plus one, when to minus one,
well, one way of trying to avoid that
could be calculate everything using the
zero method.
first, because it's so much
easier to calculate, and
then just add ones to
the left inside of the boxes.
And now you've converted it into the one
method.
Again, just as another check with E,
E is 7 and 7, early start, late start,
7 and 7, with a 1 method, it's just
increased by 1, 8 and 8.
In the 0 method, G is a 2 and a 3,
in the 1 method, it's a 3 and a 4.
It's just been increased by 1.
And that's it.
Now the question is, which method do you
actually do on the exam?
Now, for the most part, it's irrelevant
which method to use.
For the most part, right?
If they ask you simply, what is a float
of, say, B?
Now, what's the total float of B?
Well, whichever method you use, you're
still going to get the same answer, three.
Now, what is the total float of C?
Again, whichever method you use,
you get the same answer.
If they ask you for an end date,
right?
what's the early finish of C?
Early finish is 13 in the zero method,
and it's 13 in the one method.
The only time, really, it makes a
difference is if they're specifically
asking for the early start or the late
start.
What's the early start of D?
In the zero method, it's two.
In the one method, it's three.
It's just been increased by one.
One exam tip can be, now everybody is
different.
So you do what's going to work for you.
If they're asking for the one method,
right, one approach could be, calculate
everything using the zero method,
and then just add ones to the left-hand
side of the boxes to convert it to the one
method.
That might be easy for some people,
right?
But that is definitely a strategy that you
can use.
Now, the other thing
is, in the exam, they will
never, never say one
method or zero method.
They will not tell you, they will not use
those terms.
Instead, what they'll
do is, if it's relevant
to the question, they
might drop you a hint.
They might drop you a hint.
They might say something like subsequent
activities start the following week,
right, the following day, or the following
time period.
If it's a following time period,
then it's a one method.
Or if it's the same time period,
it's the zero method.
Or they may say assume a 24-hour workday,
which is a zero method.
Or assume an eight-hour workday,
which is a one method.
Okay.
Now, generally speaking, though,
if it's relevant to the question and they
don't tell you which method you should be
using, they don't drop your hint,
generally the default is the one method.
And that is the
methodology, that's a method
that's specifically been
shown in PIMBOC as well.
So you can almost assume
the one method will be
the default if, you know,
if they don't mention.
if there's no wording on whether it's a
zero method or the one method.
But again, the only difference is,
as it says here, the only difference,
early start and late start have increased
by one in the one method.
That's it.
Everything else is the same.
Critical path, float, early finish,
late finish, everything else is the same.
So you can take the zero
method, add ones to the left
and side of the boxes
for each of the activities.
Early start, late start, add a one.
you've converted it.
You've converted it into the one method.